Maine Acadian Cultural Survey Collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 3: Graphic materials, The original materials are stored at Ft. Meade.
  - Color slides, 2380 color slides
    - Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine; Farrell-Michaud house, Van Buren, Maine; Various scenes, Wallagrass, Maine, 1991, AFC 1991/029: RB-C008; Ray C. Brassieur; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document events at the Grande Riviere Festival in Van Buren, ME; 1-4, Tug-of-war between residents of Van Buren, ME, and StLeonard, New Brunswick, on the international bridge between the towns. The Canadians won; 5-7, Although there was a large crowd on the bridge, cars were allowed to pass from both sides; fieldworker David Whitman photographs the cars and crowd; 8, Sign painted especially for the Festival, with names of the three participating towns and the flags of their respective nations— St-Leonard, New Brunswick, Ste-Ouenne, France, and Van Buren, ME; These images document the Farrell-Michaud house, a large twentieth century house in Van Buren which is listed on the National Register of Historic Places. The house is currently operated as a bed-and-breakfast; 9-12, Exterior of the house; 13, Sign at the house; 14, This house, similar in style, is across the street; 15-16, Farrell-Michaud house; Miscellaneous images; 17, Sawmill with piles of shakes, Wallagrass, ME; a moose is running through the mill yard; 18-20, Cars in the parking lot at the Village Acadien in Van Buren on Native American Day, a part of the Grande Riviere Festival.
    - Native American Day, Grande Riviere Festival, Van Buren, Maine; Various scenes, Frenchville, Maine, 1991, AFC 1991/029: RB-C009; Ray C. Brassieur; 19 35mm color slides
      These images document Native American Day, and event held at the Village Acadien in Van Buren, ME, as part of the annual Grande Riviere Festival; 1-3, Purification ceremony. Mic-Mac Indian Kenny Cloud of Red Bank Reserve in New Brunswick circulates through the crowd with a smoldering sweetgrass braid; smoke from the braid is fanned with feathers to envelop each person in turn; 4-7, Sweetgrass braid is used to light ceremonial pipe; each person in attendance was then given a chance to smoke the pipe; 8, Music begins for the first dance. One of the drummers is event coordinator Guy Frigon (light blue shirt); 9, A few of the spectators; 10, The first dance; members of the audience were asked to join the dance, and some did; 11-14, Among the spectators was a group of visitors from Ste-Ouenne, France; here, the mayor of Ste-Ouenne tries on a headdress and poses with Guy Frigon (#14); Some miscellaneous images; 15, Flag, possibly a family crest, Eagle Lake; 16, Seal of the University of Maine-Fort Kent on the door of one of their official vehicles; 17, Abandoned Frenchville Starch Factory, Frenchville, ME; 18, Large storage barns called potato houses, Frenchville; this type of potato house was used to store produce prior to shipment. A number of these are still standing, but only a few are still in use; 19, Fieldworker David Whitman talks with retired railroad conductor Bob LaBonte in the Village Acadien parking lot; 20, Does not exist.
    - Village Acadien, Van Buren, Maine; Fishing on Eagle Lake, Maine; Rosaire Sirois at University of Maine-Presque Isle, Maine, 1991, AFC 1991/029: RB-C010; Ray C. Brassieur; 20 35mm color slides
      Miscellaneous images; 1, Fieldworker David Whitman talks with retired railroad worker Bob Labonte (hat) in the parking lot of the Village Acadien in Van Buren, ME; 2, Flatbed trailer, Village Acadien; 3-4, Emma LeVasseur Dubay Art Museum, Village Acadien; 5-6, Sign on gift shop roof, Village Acadien; 7, Whitman and Labonte; the building in the background is the Salle de Recreation at the Village Acadien; 8, Fishing from a small motorboat on Eagle Lake, a fairly regular sight; 9, Pontoon tour boat, Eagle Lake; These images document a visit with Rosaire Sirois at the University of Maine-Presque Isle; 10-13, Rosaire Sirois poses by his service truck, holding a picture of a brochure which describes a device Sirois invented to replace snow chains for motor vehicles; 14, Sign on Sirois' truck; 15-18, Sirois shows some of his sharpening tools and techniques; 19-20, Sirois holds pictures of Sacred Heart Catholic Church in Caribou, ME; note the ship's knees in #19.
    - Claude "Blackie" Cyr at his home, Saint David, Maine, 1991, AFC 1991/029: RB-C011; Ray C. Brassieur; 20 35mm color slides
      These images document a visit to Claude "Blackie" Cyr at his home on Long Lake in St. David, ME; 1, Blackie's daughter-in-law Arlene Devost Cyr, who is married to Blackie's son Peter, with their son. Ms. Cyr is a seamstress, and made the clothing worn by her son (including the hat); 2-12, A collection of wooden figures carved by Cyr; 13-14, Blackie's grandson; 15-16, Statue of a sailor, carved and painted by Cyr; 17-20, Arlene Devost Cyr with her son.
    - Claude "Blackie" Cyr at his home, Saint David, Maine, 1991, AFC 1991/029: RB-C012; Ray C. Brassieur; 19 35mm color slides
      These images document a visit to the home of Claude "Blackie" Cyr on Long Lake in St. David, ME; 1, Old wheelbarrow in Cyr's yard; 2-3, Smelt house, a shed used in ice-fishing for smelt on area lakes; #3, Blackie Cyr stands in front of his smelt house; 4, An assortment of Blackie's boats (including a jet ski); 5, Wheeled dock, locally called a quai (quay) on Long Lake; the wheels enable the dock to be removed from the water before the winter freeze, thus averting ice damage; 6, Terraced steps using railroad ties.
  - Black-and-white negatives, 3130 35mm black-white-film negatives
    - Field project office, University of Maine-Fort Kent, Maine; Quay on Long Lake, Sinclair, Maine; Guy Dubay, local historian; Fish River Canoe Race, Fort Kent, Maine; Documentation of a barn, Eagle Lake, Maine, June 06, 1991 - June 09, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B001-61143; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      Some miscellaneous images from the first few days in the study area; 2, Fieldworker Lisa Ornstein attempts to make peace with the Archive Assistant on her laptop computer in the office of the Maine Acadian Culture Survey at the University of Maine-Fort Kent; 3-8, Wheeled dock, locally called a "quay, examples of which are found in every lake in the study area; this quay, on Long Lake in Sinclair, ME, belongs to Jack Caron; frames #7 & 8, fieldworkers Lisa Ornstein and Ray Brassieur examine the quay; 9, Man fishing from another quay in Long Lake with pontoon aircraft moored nearby; 10-12, Local historian Guy Dubay (center) discusses project material with Brassieur and Ornstein; These images document the annual Fish River Canoe Race; 13-16, Contestants near the portage take-out point at the Fish River Falls in the Fish River Canoe Race; 17-19, Contestants and boats at the finish area of the Fish River Canoe Race; 20-23, Some of the boats raced in the Fish River Canoe Race; 24-25, Trophies awarded at the Fish River Canoe Race; These images document a visit to a barn which was being torn down in Eagle Lake, ME; 26-27, Brassieur and Ornstein examine the demolished barn belonging to Ethel Gagnon in Eagle Lake, ME. Old barns are often torn down and the wood salvaged; often the large frame timbers are used to construct a new barn. In frame #27, Mrs. Gagnon's house and tool shed are visible in the background; 28-29, Ethel Gagnon; 30-31, An outbuilding behind the house which Mrs. Gagnon called the "tool shed;" outbuildings are typical in the study area, and this appears to be one of the oldest in Eagle Lake. Design features of the outbuildings often echo those used in house construction; note the Greek Revival cornices on this shed; 32-33, Remains of the sill of the barn, typically constructed with large hewn timbers; 34, Brassieur measures one of the barn timbers; 35, Ornstein examines the remains of the barn; 36, Ground-level view of a large hewn timber used to construct the sill of the barn; this type of construction was apparently common in the 19th century, and lasted into the early 20th century; 36a, Remains of the barn.
    - Poor, Poor Woodsman Band, Fort Kent Hotel, Fort Kent, Maine; Sam Oakes' music party, Fort Kent, Maine, June 06, 1991 - June 09, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B002-61141; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the Fort Kent Hotel to hear the Poor, Poor Woodsman Band; 2-4, The Fort Kent Hotel on Main Street, Fort Kent, ME; 5-6, Fieldworker Ray Brassieur discusses the possibility of recording some of the evening's performance with Sam Oakes, fiddler and steel guitar player in the Poor, Poor Woodsman Band, in the Brass Lantern dining room of the Fort Kent Hotel. Left to right, frame # 5: Brassieur, Oakes, Oakes'sister-in-law Rina Deprey, Oakes' wife Maria (back to camera), and Rina's husband Herman Deprey, a potato grower in New Canada, ME; 7-8, Discussion continues; fieldworker Lisa Ornstein (far right) joins the group; 9, Brassieur and Oakes; 10, Band on stage just prior to starting; 11-13, Band begins to play; Brassieur sets up recording gear; 14-18, People begin to dance; 19-22, Side views of band on stage; 23, Sam Oakes on pedal steel; The following images document a music party at the home of Sam Oakes on North Perley Brook Rd. in Fort Kent, ME; 24, Brassieur sets up the microphone to tape; 25, Sam Oakes on fiddle, his brother Merrill on guitar; 26, Sam and Merrill, with John Connors in the foreground; 27-29, Sam and Merrill; 30-35, Sam; 36-Зба, Merrill.
    - Ethel Gagnon house and barn, Eagle Lake, Maine; Sam Oakes' music party, Fort Kent, Maine, June 09, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B003-61145; David A. Whitman; 37 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to a barn being torn down in Eagle Lake, ME; 1, Fieldworker Ray Brassieur examines demolished barn belonging to Ethel Gagnon of Eagle Lake, ME; 2-3, Barn debris; 4, Rear view of Ethel Gagnon's house; 5, Front view of Gagnon house; These images document a music party and family barbecue at the home of Sam Oakes on North Perley Brook Rd. in Fort Kent, ME; 6-7, Members of fiddler Sam Oakes' family seated around a kitchen table at the Oakes' house; second from right, frame # 6, is Sam's wife Maria; 8, Sam Oakes (fiddle) and his brother Merrill Oakes (guitar) play for a family music party at Sam's house on North Perley Brook Road in Fort Kent, ME; 9, Fieldworker Ray Brassieur listens to the Oakes brothers; 10, Some of Sam's family at the kitchen table; 11, Sam and Merrill play a tune while fieldworker Lisa Ornstein takes notes; 12, Ornstein takes a turn playing fiddle; 13, The music is interrupted— someone needs to see what's in the loft; 14-15, The youngest dancers at the party; 16, Sam's sister-in-law Rena Deprey videotapes the party as Sam's wife Maria watches; 17, Ornstein discusses the music with Merrill Oakes; 18, Rena Deprey videotapes; 19, Religious themes are often used in decorating houses; here, a plaque of the Ten Commandments hangs on the wall- note the ????? at the top; 20, Railing around loft, made by Sam; 21, Bear trap used by Sam's father; Sam does not use it, as he believes it is cruel; 22, Sara talks about the music; 23-27, One of the youngsters gets into the act; 28-30, Showing off a pair of "Acadian" slippers; 31-34, Sam's wife Maria and her sister-in-law Rena Voisine dance; this is the first dancing we have seen that resembles step-dancing, but is has an unusual backward slide step; 35-36, John Connor of St. Francis, ME joins the dancing; his is a more animated type of step dance with higher lifting of the feet; 36a, Sam takes up the dobro, while Ornstein plays fiddle; left to right: Brian Voisine, Merrill Oakes, Sam Oakes, Lisa Ornstein, Ray Brassieur, John Connor.
    - Bernette Albert, Acadian landing site, Albert house, Saint David, Maine, June 10, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B004-61144; David A. Whitman; 35 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      1-2, Bernette Albert gives her talk on the history of the first Acadians to populate the St. John Valley at the memorial marking the spot where the Acadians first landed; 4-8, Looking south from the memorial; note the hedgerows traversing the hillsides, which may mark property line divisions of the early land grants. These grants were done in the typically French "long lots" and measured in arpents; 9, Front view of the Albert house, which has been moved from its original location to the property owned by the Madawaska Historical Society in St. David Village. The house is a typical type built in the study area in the mid-18th century; the balustrade was likely a later addtition; 10, Side view of the Albert house; 11, Fieldworker Ray Brassieur and Madawaska Chamber of Commerce director Cathie Corey inside the Albert house; 12, Fieldworker Lisa Ornstein examines a loom; 13, Artifacts in the Albert house; 14-16, One of the looms; 17-18, A hinge on the door of an armoire; the hand-made nails indicate this piece was probably made in the early 18th century; 19-20, A woven mat which was purportedly found in the walls of the Albert house; it appears to be of Native American origin; 21-25, A part of the mat and a birch bark container which was also found in the walls of the house; 26-27, A "ship's knee" in the attic of the Albert house; these pieces were cut from the root and trunk of a hardwood tree, maintaining the natural curve of the wood.Originally a maritime construction method, these pieces were apparently used fairly often as roof supports in 18th century houses in the study area; 28-29, A section of the Albert house roof; note the ship's knee, the compound rafters, and the large timbers which form the top plate, all typical of houses in the study area; 30, Ship's knee; these were attached to the framing timbers with drift pins; 31, Another view of a roof section showing rafters and a ship's knee; 32, Brassieur and Claude "Blackie" Cyr of Madawaska examine the roof construction in the Albert house; 33, Roof construction in the Albert house; the absence of a ridgepole seems to have been universal in the constuction of buildings in the study area; 34, Another view of the rafters and the peak of the roof; 35-36, Joinery of rafters at the peak of the roof; as in many houses in the study area, the rafters are joined with a mortise and tenon and secured by a wooden peg.
    - Tante Blanche Museum, Madawaska, Maine; Paul Freeman's potato farm, Wallagrass, Maine, June 10, 1991 - June 12, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B005-61142; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the Tante Blanche Museum, operated by the Madawaska Historical Society; 1-2, Wooden replica of Liberty Bell in restored schoolhouse at the Tante Blanche Museum; 3-4, Artifacts in the Museum; 6-7, Exterior of the Museum; 8, Wrought iron cross marking the original site of the Mt. Carmel cemetery; 9-10, Sign outside a small store in St. David Village. Eshalot (the spelling varies) are a type of onion widely grown in the study area; typically, the bulbs are packed in salt water and the tops are chopped and combined with salt and herbs to make les herbes salees, which is used in flavoring soups and other dishes; These images document a visit to the potato farm of grower Herman Deprey of New Canada, ME; 11-14, Fieldworker Ray Brassieur interviews potato grower Herman Deprey in his barn; frame #11, Herman's grandson Danny stands on the tractor; 15, Herman Deprey; 16-17, Door to storage space for seed potatoes; 18, The interview continues; left to right: Brassieur, Herman Deprey, Herman's grandson Danny, Herman's son Darcey; 19-22, Three generations of Depreys discuss potato farming; 23-25, Wooden potato barrels. Such barrels, which hold 165 pounds of potatoes, were once the standard storage container when the harvest was done by hand; 26-27, Barn at Deprey Farm; many growers have similar signs with hand-painted, individualized logos; 28, House at Deprey Farm, currently occupied by Herman's parents, Mac and Blanche; 29, Herman Deprey introduces us to Paul Freeman at Freeman's house on State Highway 11 near the Soldier Pond turnoff in Wallagrass, ME; left to right: Deprey, Freeman's daughter, Freeman, Brassieur; 30, Freeman and Brassieur; 31, Freeman shows Brassieur the house; houses of this size and proportion, with simple gabled roofs, are one of the most common types found in the study area. Many of them are log houses; Freeman describes his as being "pit-sawn madrier," indicating that it is wood construction which may or may not be log; 32-36a, Scenes inside Freeman's barn; note the picture of Saint Therese and the rameaux ("blessed palm") hanging on the post. Such religious objects can be found in every type of structure in the study area; their function is to protect the building and occupants from disasters such as lightning and fire.
    - Paul Freeman home, Wallagrass, Maine; Herman Deprey and Mac Deprey home, New Canada, Maine; Various scenes, Fort Kent, Maine; Various scenes, Daigle, Maine, June 12, 1991 - June 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B006-61293; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the home of retired potato farmer Paul Freeman in Wallagrass, ME; 1-3, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur and potato grower Herman Deprey of New Canada listen to Freeman discuss the construction of this barn in the basement of the barn; 5-7, Freeman's house; 8, House and barn; 9-12, Left to right: Paul Freeman's wife Florine, Paul Freeman, their daughter Angela, in the living room; 13-15, Woodburning stove in the Freeman's kitchen, still used for cooking; A visit to the home of retired potato grower Mac Deprey of New Canada, whose son Herman has taken over the farm; 16, Brassieur interviews Mac Deprey; 17, Mac and his wife Blanche; Various scenes in Fort Kent, ME; 18-21, A house near downtown Fort Kent; 22-25, House near downtown; the small structure for firewood storage is a type seen frequently in the area.; 26, House with canoe; 27, Rear view of buildings on Main St.; These images document a stop in the village of Daigle, ME, during a trip to Van Buren, ME; 28-29, House with two decorative eagles, which are found on many homes in the study area. In addition to being the name of this village, Daigle is the family name of one of the original Acadian families to settle the upper St. John River Valley. (French d'aigle translates as of the eagle); 30-33, Marker at the cemetery in Daigle; 34, Fieldworker David Whitman takes a photograph (photographed by Ray Brassieur); 35-36a, Catholic church in Daigle.
    - Maison Morneault, Village Acadien, Van Buren, Maine; House in Van Buren, Maine, June 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B007-61299; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document the interior of the Maison Morneault, a nineteenth century house at the Village Acadien; 1-4, Birch bark insulation in the attic; 5-6, Ship's knee connecting the attic floor to the side walls; 7, Beds in the attic; 8-9, Roof support structure; the trusses are joined to the rafter with mortise-and-tenon construction held in place by a wooden peg called a trunnel; 10-13, Various views of the joinery in the attic; Miscellaneous images; 14-15, The truck of Albert Michaud, who sells the birdhouses he makes in the parking lot of the Village Acadien; These images document a visit to the house currently owned by Val Violette in Van Buren, ME; 16-19, Val Violette shows field coordinator Ray Brassieur some of the pieces removed from the house during remodeling; 20-26, Pieces of the house which were removed during remodeling; these pieces show the en coulisse construction methods often employed in the study area; 27-29, Rear of the house; the porch was a later addition, and may represent an enclosure of an outdoor summer kitchen; 30, Brassieur and Violette examine the house; 31-33, Exterior of the house; 34, Brassieur holds a piece removed from the house while talking with Val's wife Ann; These images document a visit to the Village Acadien in Van Buren, ME; 35-36, Fence at the perimeter of the Village.
    - Village Acadien, Van Buren, Maine; Albert Michaud; Gilbert Perrault; Gilbert Perrault, Wallagrass, Maine, June 15, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B008-61306; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a visit to the Village Acadien, a collection of buildings which has been placed on the National Register of Historic Places. All of the historic buildings have been moved to the site from elsewhere in the study area; 2-4, Roy house, piece-sur-piece log construction; apparently the corner joints of this house were partially sawn through so that it could be moved, and it was then reconstructed. Detail of the joinery is probably not historically accurate; 7-9, Maison Morneault, a typical Acadian house of midnineteenth century construction; the current house probably represents an enlargement of the original structure. The small addition on the far side once served as a post office; 10-19, Other buildings at the Village, including a house (11-12), a barn (13-14), a reconstruction of a log church (15-16), and a schoolhouse (17); 20-21, Field coordinator Ray Brassieur talks with birdhouse maker Albert Michaud, who sells his birdhouses from this truck parked in the lot at the Village Acadien; These images document a house and barn on the property of Gilbert Perrault in Wallagrass, ME; 22-23, Exterior of barn; Perrault (left) points out features of the barn to Brassieur; 24-28, Exterior of the house; the long and narrow proportions of this house are unusual for the study area. The large door at the rear provided carriage access; 29-30, Interior of the barn; 31-33, Sliding double doors on the barn; there is a set of double doors on each side; 34-35, Sliding mechanism on barn doors; small grooved iron wheels slid along an iron guide rail. 3 6-36a Exterior of the barn. Note that part of the lower half is sided with shakes, which provided superior insulation for the livestock kept in this section of the barn.
    - Gilbert Perrault house, Wallagrass, Maine; Documentation of various barns and buildings, Upper St. John River area, Maine, June 17, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B009-61305; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives
      These images document a house on the property of Gilbert Perrault in Wallagrass, ME. See MAP-DW-B007 for more information; 1-2, Door for carriage access at rear of house; 3-5, Perrault house as seen from State Highway 11; These images document a variety of buildings and scenes photographed while on a tour of the area with Julie Bayly and Patrick Ouellette; 6-9, Twin barn, a type found in several locations in the study area; 10, Fieldworkers Ray Brassieur and Lisa Ornstein investigate the barn with Pat Ouellette; 11, Julie Bayly photographs the barn; 12, Brassieur and Ornstein; 13-18, Corners of walls and roof of barn; 19-21, Assorted tools and equipment inside the barn; 22-23, Farmland; 24-28, Another twin barn, this one in Hamlin, ME; the gambrel roof (locally called colm-casse) is less frequent on twin barns than is the simple gabled roof, although it is a common roof type in the study area; 29-30, Interior of Hamlin twin barn; the lack of a ridgepole is nearly a nearly universal feature of area barns. The arched windows are unusual; 32-33, Side view, Hamlin twin barn; 34-36, Abandoned house across the road from Hamlin twin barn [July, 1991: the Hamlin twin barn was completely destroyed in a fire; arson is suspected].
    - Various buildings and scenes, Hamlin, Maine and St. John River area of New Brunswick, Canada, June 17, 1991 - June 19, 1991, AFC 1991/029: DW-B010-61302; David A. Whitman; 36 35 mm black-and-white film negatives